<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-08-13T13:41:39-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Kendra Albert</title><subtitle>Kendra Albert's personal website.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Enough About FOSTA’s “Unintended Consequences”</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/28/enough-about-fostas-unintended-consequences.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Enough About FOSTA’s “Unintended Consequences”" /><published>2021-07-28T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-07-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/07/28/enough-about-fostas-unintended-consequences</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/28/enough-about-fostas-unintended-consequences.html">&lt;p&gt;It feels inevitable that if you’re talking about FOSTA/SESTA (the federal law passed in 2018 that amended section 230), someone, at some point, will mention that it was aimed at combatting sex trafficking that had unintended impacts on folks doing consensual sex work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to provide a few examples, there’s a law review article about FOSTA called “&lt;a href=&quot;https://heinonline.org/HOL/LandingPage?handle=hein.journals/temple93&amp;amp;div=9&amp;amp;id=&amp;amp;page=&quot;&gt;good intentions and unintended consequences&lt;/a&gt;.”  Or you could look at the 2018 OC Register article called “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ocregister.com/2018/04/04/the-unintended-consequences-of-a-well-meaning-sex-trafficking-law/&quot;&gt;The Unintended Consequences of a Well Meaning Anti-Sex-Trafficking Law&lt;/a&gt;” (complete with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.opendemocracy.net/en/beyond-trafficking-and-slavery/guide-to-respectful-repo/&quot;&gt;cliche sexy legs&lt;/a&gt; 🙄). Even Elizabeth Warren, in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://khanna.house.gov/media/press-releases/release-reps-ro-khanna-barbara-lee-senators-elizabeth-warren-ron-wyden&quot;&gt;announcement &lt;/a&gt;for the SAFE SEX Workers Study Act, said “As lawmakers, we are responsible for examining unintended consequences of all legislation, and that includes any impact SESTA-FOSTA may have had on the ability of sex workers to protect themselves from physical or financial abuse.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cybwhoregology&quot;&gt;@cybwhoregology&lt;/a&gt; has been pointing out, the narrative of “unintended consequences” is utter nonsense. Negative effects on sex workers (and there were &lt;a href=&quot;https://hackinghustling.org/erased-the-impact-of-fosta-sesta-2020/&quot;&gt;many&lt;/a&gt;) were not “unintended.” The text of the law explicitly criminalizes the promotion of prostitution and it’s hard to argue that an interpretation of the law that was clear from its text is unintended. Sex workers and trafficking survivors were very clear about the likely outcome of FOSTA/SESTA prior to its passage. Finally, this narrative is contradicted by what the organizations that supported FOSTA say about their own goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. FOSTA explicitly criminalizes the promotion/facilitation of prostitution that does not involve trafficking.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the first conclusion I reach when I read these takes is that people have not even skimmed the text of the bill. I don’t really blame them - it’s pretty incomprehensible. But go take a look - the final text is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/PLAW-115publ164/pdf/PLAW-115publ164.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I’ll wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, do you see why it’s ahistorical to claim that negative effects on sex work were unexpected? Just in case not, I’ll break it down for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at 18 U.S.C. §2421A - the bottom of the first page. This is a federal criminal provision, created by FOSTA, prohibiting promotion or facilitation of prostitution. Note that this does not require that any sex trafficking took place. The text clearly says that it is a federal crime to run a computer service with the intent to promote or facilitate prostitution of another person.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; You can have an aggravated violation under 2421A(b) if the website promotes or facilities the prostitution of 5 or more persons, OR acts in reckless disregard of the fact that such conduct contributed to sex trafficking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am going to repeat that point again. &lt;strong&gt;You can have a criminal charge under FOSTA, including an aggravated criminal charge, without any trafficking taking place at all. Just promotion or facilitation of prostitution (aka consensual sex work).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concern is not merely hypothetical. The one criminal prosecution that has happened (US v. Martono, about CityXGuide) under 2421A just resulted in a plea deal where the defendant pled guilty to promotion of prostitution and conspiracy to facilitate prostitution. Although the Department of Justice talked about trafficking in their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.justice.gov/usao-ndtx/pr/us-attorney-s-office-shuts-down-website-promoting-prostitution-and-sex-trafficking&quot;&gt;press release&lt;/a&gt;, they never ultimately charged Martono with trafficking, likely because they could not prove that he had the level of knowledge required.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As if that wasn’t enough, FOSTA also changed Section 230 (the federal law that previously had limited internet platform’s liability) to also allow for state criminal charges against platforms based solely on conduct related to sex work, so long as the conduct underlying the charge is based on 2421A.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You cannot pass a bill that creates additional federal criminal charges and removes immunity from state criminal charges for the promotion/facilitation of prostitution and then claim that negative effects on sex work were an accident! If the people who passed this bill, and those that advocated for it, didn’t want to harm sex workers, they shouldn’t have passed a bill that created additional crimes for the promotion of prosititution.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Sex workers were incredibly clear about the likely impact of SESTA/FOSTA before and at the time of its passage.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second reason that the narrative that the negative outcomes of FOSTA on sex workers was an unintended consequence is nonsense is because it requires erasing (or ignoring) the people who pointed out contemporaneously that the bills were going to harm sex workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want receipts, there is the Survivors Against SESTA &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20180329075557if_/https://survivorsagainstsesta.org/page/3/&quot;&gt;page &lt;/a&gt;from 2018 that encouraged folks to call their Senators to explain how FOSTA/SESTA would harm sex workers. Survivors Against SESTA also produced a &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20180324175712/https://survivorsagainstsesta.files.wordpress.com/2018/03/onlinespaces_impact-003.pdf&quot;&gt;one-pager &lt;/a&gt;on why sex workers need online spaces. Oh, and here’s their &lt;a href=&quot;https://survivorsagainstsesta.files.wordpress.com/2018/03/sestafosta_1p_senate.pdf&quot;&gt;one-pager &lt;/a&gt;on how FOSTA and SESTA would harm workers. New Orleans Harm Reduction has &lt;a href=&quot;https://nolaharmreduction.tumblr.com/post/171627547809/all-the-info-you-need-to-fight-back-against&quot;&gt;a page from 2018&lt;/a&gt; where sex workers outlined materials as part of the social media campaign against FOSTA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Media even covered these concerns! Here’s a contemporaneous &lt;a href=&quot;https://theappeal.org/proposed-federal-trafficking-legislation-has-surprising-opponents-advocates-who-work-with-bf418c73d5b4/&quot;&gt;article from Melissa Gira Grant&lt;/a&gt; quoting sex workers’ rights experts about the negative impact of either FOSTA or SESTA on sex workers. And there’s a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fastcompany.com/40537286/fosta-backlash-how-the-anti-sex-trafficking-bill-could-harm-sex-workers&quot;&gt;FastCompany article&lt;/a&gt; with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/KateDAdamo/status/968216597570752512&quot;&gt;tweet from Kate D’Adamo&lt;/a&gt;, who said “I was a #sexworker organizer for years in NYC. #FOSTA would undermine almost every single thing I would tell people for how to stay alive. ALL screening, ALL peer references, ALL bad date lists I could send. #SurvivorsAgainstFOSTA.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also worth checking out the #LetUsSurvive or #SurvivorsAgainstSESTA hashtag, where you can still find many of the posts that people made prior to FOSTA’s passage. (Although the historical record is obviously incomplete because of account deletions, caused in part by platforms’ fear of liability under FOSTA. I believe Alanis Morissette would call that ironic.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FOSTA and SESTA were two bills that were advocated for by different organizations that were combined into one, giant, bad, law. If SESTA alone was passed, it would have been plausible to argue that anti-sex work effects were collateral damage to efforts to prevent sex trafficking, if not for the accurate predictions about consequences of the bill. In short, sex workers expected these consequences, and said quite clearly that these were the likely outcomes. To quote Bardot Smith, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://hackinghustling.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/ALGORITHMIC-WARFARE-hh-feb2020.pdf&quot;&gt;WHORES TOLD YOU&lt;/a&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Many of the people who advocated for the bill saw increasing the difficulty of engaging in consensual sex work as a feature of the bill, not a bug.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Content warning for language that ignores sex worker agency - skip the next paragraph if that’s harmful to you.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not just that calling the effects unintended erases sex workers’ advocacy and labor. It also ignores the fact that some people who oppose “sex trafficking” often do want to eliminate all sex work. For example, one supporter of the bills was CATW (the Coalition Against Trafficking in Women). CATW explicitly seeks to end what they call “sexual exploitation,” which it defines as possible “only if no woman or girl is trafficked, exploited or prostituted in the sex trade.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; So from the angle of organizations like CATW, as well as the National Center on Sexual Exploitation (formerly known as Morality in Media), and others, the harm to sex workers (who they often do not believe are legitimate stakeholders) is, in fact, a feature, not a bug. If you’re looking for a useful summary of how this dynamic plays out in reporting, I suggest this piece from &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyy.org/segments/fosta-sesta-was-supposed-to-thwart-sex-trafficking-instead-its-sparked-a-movement/&quot;&gt;WHYY Philadelphia&lt;/a&gt;. In it, someone who works for CATW and who is speaking from their experience being trafficked makes the claim that “Sex is not work, and work is not sex. And although I recognize that there is a population of people who self-identify as sex workers, it’s really a term that’s used to mask the inherent harms that come with prostitution.” That’s not a statement that is consistent with the idea that harm to sex workers is an unintended result of anti-trafficking efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this debate goes back far further than section 230 - it’s a rehashing of a set of conversations that took place during the white feminist sex wars of the 1970s. Far more eloquent people than I have written about how it is true that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://nplusonemag.com/issue-35/essays/cashconsent/&quot;&gt;binary between sex trafficking and sex work does not do a good job of capturing folks’ experiences, but that’s because it is a product of whorephobia&lt;/a&gt;. Whorephobia comes down to the idea that there is something uniquely damaging about work that involves sex, rather than the damage coming from society’s distaste for sex work and the stigma that comes along with that and criminalization.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (Just to be clear - there is not. Many of the harms that people articulate as coming from this kind of work come from criminalization itself, as well as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6424363/&quot;&gt;the lack of affirming health and social services&lt;/a&gt;.) Fundamentally, it is impossible to truly respect and listen to sex workers and believe that the goal should be the elimination of sex work, unless you also believe that all work should be eliminated.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To pull us back to FOSTA, I suspect most mainstream technology policy organizations (and reporters, and pundits/scholars) do not want to comment on or engage with the fact that some (but not, by any means, all) anti-sex trafficking organizations believe that all sex work is inherently exploitive or leads to sex trafficking. Thus, the argumentative move seems to be to suggest that the intentions of the people who promoted FOSTA/SESTA were good and the harm to sex workers was unexpected. I understand this from a realpolitik perspective - the politics of the anti-trafficking space can seem complicated, and no one wants to appear to be pro-trafficking. And admitting you’ve caused harm is hard! However, again, pretending that prostitution was “accidentally included” or that FOSTA was a bill that was only aimed at ending what the law defines as sex trafficking is at best, revisionism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people who talk about FOSTA’s unintended consequences are not bad people, nor are they trying to erase or ignore sex workers. But the narrative that sex workers were “collateral damage” of an anti-trafficking bill is ahistorical and compounds the harm. Please, please, stop saying that the effects were unintended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you find this post useful? Please throw some money at Hacking//Hustling, who has been working to cultivate a better understanding of the impacts of FOSTA. You can donate &lt;a href=&quot;https://hackinghustling.org/donate/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to Danielle Blunt and Riana Pfefferkorn, who provided very helpful feedback on this post! All mistakes are my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- Footnotes themselves at the bottom. --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;18 U.S.C. §2421A(a). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Thank you to Kate D’Adamo, who pointed this out. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;18 U.S.C. §2421(a)(5)(C). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The empirical evidence is clear that criminalization harms sex workers. See, e.g., Platt, Lucy, Pippa Grenfell, Rebecca Meiksin, Jocelyn Elmes, Susan G. Sherman, Teela Sanders, Peninah Mwangi, and Anna-Louise Crago. 2018. “Associations between Sex Work Laws and Sex Workers’ Health: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis of Quantitative and Qualitative Studies.” PLoS Medicine 15 (12): e1002680. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is from CATW’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://catwinternational.org/our-work/advocating-for-strong-laws/&quot;&gt;description of their work&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Melissa Gira Grant’s Playing the Whore: The Work of Sex Work is an excellent resource that more fully explores this idea. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;This is an argument from Moses Moon (fka @thotscholar) Sex Work as Anti-Work body of thinking. You can read them more fully exploring it, in conversation with Lorelei Lee and Kitty Milford, &lt;a href=&quot;https://hackinghustling.org/event-work-and-anti-work-what-are-people-in-the-sex-trades-fighting-for/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It feels inevitable that if you’re talking about FOSTA/SESTA (the federal law passed in 2018 that amended section 230), someone, at some point, will mention that it was aimed at combatting sex trafficking that had unintended impacts on folks doing consensual sex work.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Care, Not Respect: Teaching Professionalism</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/15/care-not-respect-teaching-professionalism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Care, Not Respect: Teaching Professionalism" /><published>2021-07-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-07-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/07/15/care-not-respect-teaching-professionalism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/15/care-not-respect-teaching-professionalism.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was inspired by a conversation with my 2020-2021 student, Kose, as well as conversations with this year’s IfRFA fellows. Thank you Kose, Elias, Iltaff, Nirali, and Makela! &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone who has to articulate to students what clear standards look like in a profession that lacks them, I always worry about using the word “professionalism.”  What is professionalism, and how does one teach it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its best, professionalism encompasses a number of small, everyday tasks that I associate with high quality work products or making life easier for those around us. Common tasks that fall under the professionalism umbrella include wearing the correct clothes to court, reviewing final work product to make sure the formatting is perfect, or showing up on time and with an agenda to meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s wrong with that? In so many legal spaces, professionalism comes to stand in for the unnamable, the je ne sais quoi.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It means “looks like us” or “acts like us.” Professionalism implicitly relies on the stereotypes about who belongs in law and who does not. Every time I facilitate discussions about this, I learn about new things piss me off. Some examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First generation students are told that during oral argument, you shouldn’t use hand gestures because it’s unprofessional.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Female students are held to dress code requirements that only work for some bodies, not to mention some budgets.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Students of color are expected to constantly code switch to fit the idea of what a legal practitioner looks like.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neurodivergent students get told to make eye-contact in meetings where it doesn’t make a damn bit of difference other than making a supervisor feel more powerful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The list goes on and on and on. Unprofessional becomes the catch all for “not acting like me,” when deployed by white, straight, often male, supervisors. Professionalism is so racist, ableist, classist, and sexist that it feels like it can’t be rescued from itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a student dares to ask why these things matter, professionalism is usually framed in terms of respect for legal institutions. We stand when the judge enters because it is respectful. We wear a suit to court because we respect the institution. But as someone who is often disrespected or harmed by legal institutions, I find it hard to act from this frame. Call me petty, but legal institutions so rarely go out of their way to respect me or the people I care about. Performing respect for them doesn’t get me out of bed in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But over time, I’ve come to believe there are some skills at the heart of professionalism that might be worth saving, and as a teacher, I am always trying to balance teaching the way things should be with the way things are. So when I have to teach it, I try to talk about professionalism as a way of caring about others around us. Professionalism, at its best, is as an act of love and belief towards those we work with, rather than a set of behavioral standards that we have to live up to. We review final documents for typos because taking the time to produce high quality, clean, work product shows our clients that they matter to us. We send agendas, and show up on time because we care about those we’re meeting with, and not wasting their time is a way to express that care. And when these norms do not communicate care - when they will not succeed in making our people feel cared for, we can let them go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Framing professionalism as an act of care for others also helps us build skills in setting boundaries. There are some things I won’t do, no matter how much I care about my client or my students. Each person may decide for themselves what steps they may take to care for others, and what steps they cannot take out of care for themselves. I am not going to accept being misgendered, even if it would be “disrespectful” to interrupt someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reframing, of course, does not solve all professionalism’s problems.  As Kose pointed out to me, care can be weaponized in toxic ways - see the discourse around viewing a workplace as a family, which often makes it harder to assert reasonable boundaries. And care work requirements still disproportionately fall on minoritized people, and that means we must be vigilant in our views about who needs to be professional. But if professionalism is about care, we can use this frame to ask for more from the students (and lawyers) who traditionally perform less care work. Taking notes, doing ministerial tasks, prepping for meetings, “acting professional” - these are things we can redistribute among team members, when we acknowledge them as grounded in care, not respect. We can accept dress codes for the utter horseshit that they are and still follow them, because we care about our clients.  For me, this reframe helps solve a fundamental problem - how to both understand professionalism’s role in gatekeeping the profession, but still teach it in ways that allow students to see how it might matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- Footnotes themselves at the bottom. --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;When I went to look up how to spell “je ne sais quoi”, the sample sentence that shows up from Oxford dictionaries is literally “that je ne sais quoi that makes a professional.” (!) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This was inspired by a conversation with my 2020-2021 student, Kose, as well as conversations with this year’s IfRFA fellows. Thank you Kose, Elias, Iltaff, Nirali, and Makela!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">June 2021 Decrim MA Testimony</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/June2021DecrimTestimony/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="June 2021 Decrim MA Testimony" /><published>2021-06-16T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-06-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/decrim-ma-testimony</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/June2021DecrimTestimony/">&lt;p&gt;On June 15, 2021, in solidarity with a number of my sex working comrades, I offered oral testimony to the Massachusetts Joint Committee on the Judiciary in favor of decriminalizing common nightwalking and against the Nordic model (also known as End Demand, or rather ironically, “the Equality Model”). I’m reposting it here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chair Eldridge, Chair Day, and the Members of the Committee on the Judiciary,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for having me today. My name is Kendra Albert, and I am an attorney at Harvard Law School, where I teach in the Cyberlaw Clinic. I am also an out transgender person, and I serve as the Director of the Initiative for a Representative First Amendment. My practice at the Cyberlaw Clinic focuses on the free speech impacts of regulation of sex work. I am here today to oppose bill &lt;a href=&quot;https://malegislature.gov/Bills/192/HD3437&quot;&gt;H.1761/S.940&lt;/a&gt; and to support bill &lt;a href=&quot;https://malegislature.gov/Bills/192/H1800&quot;&gt;H.1800/S.992&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Massachusetts has long been a national leader in evidence-based policy.   What we know about sex work, both from what sex workers tell us and from research, is that harm to sex workers comes primarily from stigma and criminalization, not from the work itself. Because of that, repealing common nightwalking is vital - it removes one avenue that police use to profile sex workers and people who police believe look like sex workers. But merely erasing the most antiquated language while continuing to incentivize police targeting clients, as H.1761 does, just moves the problem around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making Massachusetts follow the evidence leads to supporting full decriminalization, not asymmetric criminalization under the guise of helping sex workers access exit services. Studies show that the model suggested by the advocates of H.1761/S.940 (generally called the “Nordic Model”) leads to reluctance to call police for help and may exacerbate violence. A peer-reviewed study released in Social Science of five “nordic” jurisdictions in Canada found that almost one third of sex workers surveyed would be unable to call 911 if there was an emergency.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In another study from Montreal, sex workers reported dramatic increases in violence after Nordic-style policing was implemented.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In fact, sex workers in Canada have had to file lawsuits to try to end human rights harms that comes from these failed policies. There is no evidence that the Nordic model reduces demand for sex work, nor that it reduces human trafficking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sex workers in Massachusetts deserve better than a policy intervention that has already failed elsewhere. For those reasons, I encourage you to support full decriminalization, H.1867, or as an interim step, the full repeal of the common nightwalking crime, H.1800/S.992, rather than providing favorable reviews on H.1761/S.940.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your time and the opportunity to testify.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Crago A-L, Bruckert C, Braschel M, Shannon K. Sex Workers’ Access to Police Assistance in Safety Emergencies and Means of Escape from Situations of Violence and Confinement under an “End Demand” Criminalization Model: A Five City Study in Canada. Social Sciences. 2021; 10(1):13. https://doi.org/10.3390/socsci10010013. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Chu, S. K. (2013). Sex Work Law Reform in Canada: Considering Problems with the Nordic Model. Alberta Law Review, 51(1). Retrieved from http://www.aidslaw.ca/site/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/Nordic_model-ALR-Oct2013.pdf &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">On June 15, 2021, in solidarity with a number of my sex working comrades, I offered oral testimony to the Massachusetts Joint Committee on the Judiciary in favor of decriminalizing common nightwalking and against the Nordic model (also known as End Demand, or rather ironically, “the Equality Model”). I’m reposting it here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Evaluating Apologies</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/apologycriteria/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evaluating Apologies" /><published>2021-04-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-04-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/evaluating-apologies</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/apologycriteria/">&lt;p&gt;I wrote this a while ago, but it seems relevant today - these are my own personal criteria for evaluating apologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apologies from a person who did or was complicit in a harmful act must be meaningful and consonant with the magnitude of the harm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically, in order for me personally to find it meaningful, the apology must include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;naming the harm that they did, specifically
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Leaving others to explain or contextualize the shitty thing is not acceptable.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;explaining how they became aware that harm was done
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If appropriate, crediting people who attempted to intervene or report.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stating very clearly what exact steps they are taking to make it right, including a description of how those steps address problems they caused
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Giving money to a cause is insufficient if giving money to a cause would not ensure that the harmful thing would not happen again.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stating who will hold them accountable for those steps.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It is not appropriate to expect those harmed to hold them accountable.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Everyone often in practice means no one - it is better to be specific.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;In some circumstances it may be appropriate to pay someone (up front) to help the person with their accountability.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The apology must not:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;trivializing the harm caused (no “I’m sorry if you were offended.”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prioritize excuses, explaining their thought process, or centering themselves over the harm caused&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The person apologizing must also have mitigated or attempted to mitigate harm caused by any protective steps they took or an institution took on their behalf. Even the most heartfelt apology is hard to take seriously if someone is still threatening legal action against whistleblowers or stonewalling further investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is a specific person who has been most significantly harmed by the bad action, their views on the acceptability of a public response are important to me but not controlling of whether I think an apology is meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clarifying Questions:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But what about some specific circumstance where these rules don’t make sense?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a good question! Obviously, each situation is unique, and there may be instances where some of the items here are not going to be applicable. But if I find myself trying to rules lawyer myself into thinking that an apology merits forgiveness or public support, that’s a good opportunity to check myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But an apology like the one you suggest would expose someone to liability!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good! Or shall I say - that is part of being held accountable, because it represents a person accepting at least some of consequences of their actions, to the extent that the legal system dispenses those. It also means that the apologizer is willing to give up something of value to deal with the harm they have caused, which can be an important test of their seriousness.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I wrote this a while ago, but it seems relevant today - these are my own personal criteria for evaluating apologies.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Chatham House Should Not Rule</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/chatamhouse" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Chatham House Should Not Rule" /><published>2021-04-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-04-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/chathamhouse</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/chatamhouse">&lt;p&gt;I often attend events that use the Chatham House Rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“When a meeting, or part thereof, is held under the Chatham House Rule, participants are free to use the information received, but neither the identity nor the affiliation of the speaker(s), nor that of any other participant, may be revealed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chatham House-by-default seems to have become a norm in certain parts of academia and civil society. Academic institutions often use it because not attributing allows for participation/insights from people who may have institutional constraints on sharing their experiences/opinions. For example, folks who work for a government entity or a corporation are often constrained in what they are able to say. Using the Chatham House Rule allows them to speak/participate.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for those of us who are not subject to those institutional strictures and who have often given up opportunities to remain so, Chatham-by-default can mean that our participation in these conversations is just unacknowledged (and usually unpaid) labor. If I say something useful or valuable during a conversation, and it makes it into a concrete output (like a report), the Chatham House Rule ensures that I don’t receive any credit for that outside the context of the people who were potentially in the room in the first place. If others find the idea compelling and end up repeating it, I may never get credit, making it harder to build credibility as an expert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relying on memory rather than formal credit also has distributional consequences because of sexism and racism. Not recording attribution is likely to have disproportionately negative effects on those who are already less likely to be recognized as having important contributions. (This phenomenon is sometimes called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/what-is-hepeating-2017-9&quot;&gt;“he-peating” or “rewhiting.”&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many interpretations of the Chatham House Rule produce summary documents that don’t allow for an understanding of power dynamics or the incentives of speakers. It matters who said what! If the [Big Company] lobbyist says that the problem is that not enough people trust corporations to do the right thing, a reader should weigh that comment differently than if someone who works for [Consumer Rights Group] says that. Positionality beyond affiliations is also relevant - especially as we think about underrepresentation of Black, Latinx, and Indigenous people in spaces like technology policy. (We could also imagine a version of the rule that allows for some sharing of information about the background of a speaker. One difficulty could be that such information requires a sufficient number of speakers of a particular background in the room so that an identification is not immediately revealing.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the Chatham House rule seems to operate on an implicit assumption that additional information is sufficient reward for participation in conversations, as opposed to credit for insights/perspectives. As someone who believes incredibly strongly in paying participants for their time and efforts, I’m increasingly uncomfortable with academic norms that lead to extractive knowledge creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Chatham House Rule, as a default practice with no option of attribution, privileges the needs of those who are not willing to have their views be attributed over people who benefit from attribution and credit.&lt;/strong&gt; I wish more organizers would think critically about whose participation is rewarded and encouraged by Chatham House, rather than assuming that it is good for everyone. As part of this process, organizers could directly consult participants in knowledge creation about what is useful to them - whether that’s payment, anonymity, or credit, and then endeavor to provide that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to Jonathan Zittrain, Afsaneh Rigot, Wendy Seltzer, and some anonymous reviewers who read and provided feedback on a draft. Very meta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- Footnotes themselves at the bottom. --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;This is fundamentally different from safety rules that are used to protect at risk people. Across many spaces, I have never heard the Chatham House Rule used in that context. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I often attend events that use the Chatham House Rule.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Their Law: New Essay on Harvard Law Review Blog</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/07/11/their-law-new-essay-on-harvard-law-review-blog.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Their Law: New Essay on Harvard Law Review Blog" /><published>2019-07-11T11:20:07-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-11T11:20:07-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/07/11/their-law-new-essay-on-harvard-law-review-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/07/11/their-law-new-essay-on-harvard-law-review-blog.html">&lt;p&gt;I recently published &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.harvardlawreview.org/their-law/&quot;&gt;an essay&lt;/a&gt; responding to &lt;em&gt;They, Them, and __Theirs&lt;/em&gt;, an article on non-binary inclusion. (Yes, the title is a reference to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Qz9I0WJxF84&quot;&gt;The Prodigy song&lt;/a&gt;.) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;tmblr-full&quot; data-orig-height=&quot;3840&quot; data-orig-width=&quot;5760&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://66.media.tumblr.com/74849cc16b1336081552f432355db075/1207ac2d689146ca-c6/s540x810/68ff3d8e86319c431ab40116c2257f8f4ca65472.jpg&quot; data-orig-height=&quot;3840&quot; data-orig-width=&quot;5760&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll quote the beginning here: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Many gender-neutral restrooms and locker rooms are behind locked doors.  Not in the same sense that all bathroom doors are locked; rather, these spaces can be accessed only by either being lucky enough to slip in behind someone with authorization, or by pleading one’s case before some sort of decision maker—a literal gatekeeper.  In the most immediate sense, it’s the gym manager (“Can I use the temporary gender neutral facility?”), the information desk person (“Can you let me into the family restroom?”), or the key card provisioner (“I need access to the other floor because that’s where the bathroom I can use is. Please.”).&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Other aspects of gender-neutral life can require a different, but intimately related, set of recitations to a more metaphorical set of gatekeepers.  Sometimes these pleas are heard by a therapist (“Can you give me a diagnosis so I can get this covered by my insurance?”), a doctor (“Please just let me have the anti-depressants so I don’t become another suicide statistic.”), or a judge (“Your honor, don’t make me publish my old name and new name in the newspaper in order to effectuate my name change.”).  Other times they are addressed to an HR manager (“My colleague called me by the wrong pronouns for the entire meeting and my boss didn’t correct him.”), a lawyer (“The new shift manager kept snickering about my pronoun pin and marked me as late even when I wasn’t…do you think I have a case?”), or an athletics organizing body (“Look, I just want to lift weights, okay? I don’t care which category I’m in.”).&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;It is the law that underlies these requests that Professor Jessica Clarke takes up in &lt;a href=&quot;https://harvardlawreview.org/2019/01/they-them-and-theirs/&quot;&gt;They, Them, and Theirs&lt;/a&gt;, her law review article on nonbinary people.  Rather than focusing on the moral claim that nonbinary people should have their genders taken seriously, Clarke takes up the logistical arguments that critics have mounted against nonbinary gender claims.  Most simply, she argues that including nonbinary people in existing social institutions would not require radical changes to the law.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Clarke’s thesis is not wrong.  She ably points out many ways in which nonbinary people can fit easily into existing systems and pushes back against common arguments, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2016/01/13/462906419/everyone-uses-singular-they-whether-they-realize-it-or-not&quot;&gt;from the tyranny of grammar&lt;/a&gt; to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://time.com/4702962/gender-neutral-bathrooms/&quot;&gt;imagined threat of sexual predators in restrooms&lt;/a&gt;.  There is certainly a strategic argument to support the integration of nonbinary people into existing systems of state-sponsored gender.  But advocates for nonbinary people should not start with a goal of assimilation, even if that is where they end.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the rest at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.harvardlawreview.org/their-law/&quot;&gt;https://blog.harvardlawreview.org/their-law/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image from Vice’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://broadlygenderphotos.vice.com/&quot;&gt;Gender Spectrum Collection.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I recently published an essay responding to They, Them, and __Theirs, an article on non-binary inclusion. (Yes, the title is a reference to a The Prodigy song.) </summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Baking as Carework</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/03/24/baking-as-carework.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Baking as Carework" /><published>2019-03-24T13:33:19-04:00</published><updated>2019-03-24T13:33:19-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/03/24/baking-as-carework</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/03/24/baking-as-carework.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;tmblr-full&quot; data-orig-height=&quot;2053&quot; data-orig-width=&quot;4017&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://66.media.tumblr.com/58e78c10651fe4ced33826c478c0f221/tumblr_inline_povshy2Y641rrgb56_540.jpg&quot; data-orig-height=&quot;2053&quot; data-orig-width=&quot;4017&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I changed my mind about bringing baked goods into the office. Twice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t always had strong opinions on this complex and important topic. But in 2012, I brought in cookies for a meeting. I was nominally in charge of a large group of folks, and I figured as a courtesy, I would bake some cookies to make everyone feel better about having to attend on less than 24-hours’ notice. They were complicated cookies - Christina Tosi’s chocolate chip marshmallow cornflake cookies. I overanalyzed how many people had eaten. Who went back for seconds. If they liked them. And as the cookies disappeared, I felt as if my authority to actually lead the meeting was disintegrating - crumbling into the carpet along with the stray crumbs. They were delicious. I swore “never again.” No more baked goods in the office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t a totally unreasonable position. I haven’t been able to track down a citation, but I’ve heard that Sheryl Sandberg once said that you should never bring baked goods into the office. The unspoken end of that sentence is “if you’re a woman.” You should never bring baked goods into the office if you’re a woman (or read as one). Because then you’ll be a mom, rather than a leader, a nurturer rather than a respected colleague. And if you had to choose (and it certainly seems like you did have to choose), wouldn’t you pick “respected” over “comforting”? I would. I did. Besides, opting-out of feminine labor as a feminine presenting-person felt radical. It felt transgressive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t just that I had brought cookies into that meeting. I cared about what people thought about them. And that was the second problem - just baking cookies shows that you spent time and energy on taking care of others, a no-no - but desperately wanting people to like your baked goods is even worse. Caring about what other people think gives them power over you, and giving people who have to respect you power over you was scary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing my mind about my no baked goods policy wasn’t a bolt from the blue. I didn’t wake up one morning, shout “the patriarchy is full of lies! good leaders can be vulnerable and show that they care!” and bake a whole pan of brownies for my colleagues. It was a slow process, like sugar caramelizing on the Great British Baking Show, where nothing appears to be changing until the entire pan is almost burnt. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I took a class from an amazing biological anthropologist who baked for us, her students, every week, I didn’t respect her less. When I read Teaching to Transgress and bell hooks talked about the importance of being vulnerable and present in order to create a learning environment, I found myself nodding along. I thought about how many more risks I was willing to take with colleagues who were open about their struggles and uncertainty.  I followed a long conversation around emotional labor online and reflected upon how I loved the feminist spaces, where people put time, energy and attention into creating dialogue. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time, I watched who was able to not focus on the feelings of those around them. I could, as a “scholar”, but my friend, the administrative assistant, she didn’t have that option. The black women I chatted with at conferences couldn’t – they’d be perceived as angry. My younger colleagues, who worked for male bosses who weren’t quite as secure as mine – they couldn’t get away with not performing emotional labor and femininity in the workplace.  I grew more uncomfortable opting out of care work just because I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, I found a thousand counter-examples to my initial thesis that there was a transgressive power to just opting out. In a society where vulnerability and care are devalued and seen as a sign of weakness, care-work, like baking, is radical.  Sometimes it is more transgressive to opt-in. To choose to do the work, even though you know you don’t (or shouldn’t) have to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now believe that vulnerability and visible care are not at odds with leadership and respect. They are inseparable. Admitting that you care, that you are willing to put in the time and energy, is fundamental to showing those around you that you respect them. And giving respect is a good way to earn it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll never quite know if I was right, in 2012, that I was respected less because I baked for people. It’s not clear if my confidence in embracing carework now come from the sense that I am more confident I am better at my job, more sure that I am worthy of respect (not to mention a better baker). But one way out of the trap of patriarchy, where you are damned if you do and damned if you don’t, is to do what you would have wanted to do anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now I bake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This essay is a slightly modified version of the talk I gave as part of the Harvard Law School Library’s Why I Changed My Mind event. You can watch the talk &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?time_continue=3111&amp;amp;v=R7DY7DgOsdU&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Difficult Speech in Feminist Communities</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/03/05/difficult-speech-in-feminist-communities.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Difficult Speech in Feminist Communities" /><published>2019-03-05T07:57:55-05:00</published><updated>2019-03-05T07:57:55-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/03/05/difficult-speech-in-feminist-communities</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/03/05/difficult-speech-in-feminist-communities.html">&lt;p&gt;(This essay was originally published in 2017, as part of the Berkman Klein Center’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dash.harvard.edu/handle/1/33746096&quot;&gt;Perspectives on Harmful Speech Online&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; collection. In the interest of making it more broadly sharable, I’m now posting it here.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many feminist communities online have developed sets of practices to accommodate, moderate and regulate speech. As we consider the implications of hateful speech on our online communities, it is vital that we also reflect upon how communities deliberatively deal with wanted yet complicated topics, and whether these practices can provide models for dealing with formulating and regulating speech according to community-developed norms. This essay discusses one such set of models – a set of interventions against what I call “difficult speech.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficult speech is speech that is wanted yet may also cause discomfort or harm in a community with a shared set of norms. For example, a trans person in a community aimed at trans folks might want to discuss their body as part of seeking advice on dysphoria (a psychological condition of distress stemming from one’s body not matching one’s gender). However, for other trans folks, a person’s recounting of their feelings about their body may not be something that they cannot read without having suicidal thoughts. The issue is further complicated by the fact that what may cause difficulty for a person on their bad day might be perfectly fine a few days later. This variability, both across people and time, creates unique moderation needs. In writing this piece, I reviewed a small number (~5) of feminist sites, including both blogs with moderated comments sections and forums/private community spaces, to see how they deal with difficult speech. Content warnings and multiple channels with redirection are two options for handling this moderation that were common to multiple surveyed spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Using Content Warnings to Offset the Impact of Difficult Speech&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most obvious method of dealing with difficult speech is “content warnings” or “trigger warnings.” Content warnings are literal statements of the content of following text or images – for example, if a text contained the first-person narrative of sexual assault, a content warning might say “sexual assault.” (Generally, the term “content warning” is considered broader than “trigger warning” and thus I will use it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Content warnings are not unique to feminist communities, but are often more common in feminist spaces than elsewhere. Warnings can be used in a variety of circumstances, for content containing anything from depictions of rape to manifestations of white supremacy. In some communities, warnings are deployed along with tags that make the difficult material not readable unless moused over (“spoiler tags”). If material is not obscured, a content warning can be paired with a note about how long the warning will be in effect for (“CN: police violence, next 4 paragraphs”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities often engage in discursive practices around what kinds of content requires a warning – allowing autonomy and discussion over shared values. Commonly chosen content warnings among some feminist communities surveyed include “sexual assault”, “transphobia”, “racism”, “war on agency” (reproductive rights), and “Nazis.” As demonstrated by this list, the potential options are broad, and often depend on the needs and characteristics of the members of the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Using Multiple Channels to Respond to Difficult Speech&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some communities use a combination between multiple channels and conversation redirection to handle difficult speech. For example, there might be two channels for a particular issue: #bodyissues and #bodyissues-unfiltered. When someone wants to talk about something that others might find difficult, either as explicitly mentioned in guidelines or just understood as a sensitive topic, they might post in #bodyissues with a content warning and a pointer – “I want to talk about a dysmorphia thing in unfiltered, if you’re up for listening meet me there.” Users who are able to support can view #bodyissues-unfiltered to read and comment. Other users who might not be worried about potential triggers can view the unfiltered channel as part of their daily community interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, a user who is finding a conversation taking place in the #bodyissues tag difficult can ask other users to move to #bodyissues-unfiltered. This allows for more situational reactivity than a more traditional content warning system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Platforms, Affordances and Regulation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One notable characteristic of the aforementioned interventions that deal with difficult speech is that they rely on platforms having particular affordances, and making these affordances accessible to moderators – the power to ban members, to create multiple channels, and to block out speech (for example, with spoiler tags). Thus, difficult speech interventions may not be possible in communities that work on platforms without these. For example, a community on Facebook, couldn’t use spoiler tags, as they are unsupported by the platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, difficult speech interventions can be undermined by more traditional moderation actions by platforms. For example, imagine a racial slur is used in the context of explaining a recent experience and asking for reassurance. If an appropriate content warning is used, the harmful effects on members of the targeted community may be mitigated. Nevertheless, the post containing the slur might trigger a “shadowban” or “time out” from the platform due to the language – resulting in fewer people seeing the post at all, the exact opposite of what the user may need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I write this essay, Mastodon, an alternative social network, has been rapidly gaining popularity. Mastodon supports content warnings, and users from different Mastodon servers have been engaged in robust debate over what content deserves warnings, from politics to porn. Whether Mastodon ends up going the way of forgotten social networks like Diaspora or Ello or becomes widely adopted, it is notable that content warnings are now more integrated directly into platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since much regulation of speech is bound up in legal frameworks and debates over banned terms, community adaptations to difficult speech, like those taking place on feminist platforms or on Mastodon, suggest a new way forward for dealing with harmful speech online.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">(This essay was originally published in 2017, as part of the Berkman Klein Center’s Perspectives on Harmful Speech Online collection. In the interest of making it more broadly sharable, I’m now posting it here.)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making Your In-Person Event Inclusive of Non-Binary People</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/03/02/nonbinaryinclusive.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making Your In-Person Event Inclusive of Non-Binary People" /><published>2018-03-02T15:56:55-05:00</published><updated>2018-03-02T15:56:55-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/03/02/nonbinaryinclusive</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/03/02/nonbinaryinclusive.html">&lt;p&gt;When I attend events, I’m often the first out non-binary person that the organizers have ever invited. Many times, I am the first out non-binary person they have ever met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure data-orig-width=&quot;640&quot; data-orig-height=&quot;480&quot; class=&quot;tmblr-full&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://66.media.tumblr.com/dc39da571b6678af521fe4fb0ec3d21f/tumblr_inline_p4z136mWZn1rrgb56_540.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; data-orig-width=&quot;640&quot; data-orig-height=&quot;480&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image: graffiti on a wall that says “Gender Queer” in black text with pink and green highlights. CC-BY 2.0, Charles Hutchins.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, I’d like to offer some guidance for a host who would like to make an in-person event (like a conference, meet up, or panel) more welcoming to non-binary folks. These steps may also make the space more inclusive to other trans folks, as well as potentially folks from other historically marginalized or underrepresented groups, but I am going to focus on interventions around non-binary inclusivity. Of course, this is drawn from my own experience – different people might have different suggestions or requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This stuff is important because non-inclusive events are difficult to attend. At the most basic level, it costs me time and emotional energy when people fail to think about how to make their events more inclusive. Every moment I spend educating a fellow attendee or speaker is time I cannot spend doing the work that I was invited to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My general advice can be summed up in three rules:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you don’t know, ask.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you can’t control, acknowledge.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you screw up, apologize and take steps to fix it.&lt;/strong&gt;  
&lt;!-- more --&gt;
    &lt;h2 id=&quot;if-you-dont-know-ask&quot;&gt;If you don’t know, ask.&lt;/h2&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of being welcoming to non-binary folk is to let go of assumptions about how to understand or treat people’s gender. I would almost always rather be asked beforehand about something rather than have the organizer make a guess. This can range from simple stuff, like what things would make a conference more welcoming to me, to more complicated and delicate topics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a positive example, when an organization had to book a flight for me, the organizer realized that in order to book they had to provide a binary gender marker. They asked how to proceed and if I had a preference about which one they chose. To me, this was incredibly affirming – they needed binary identification information from me, they made clear why, and they let me tell them what I wanted them to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was much better than just guessing which one to pick, even if they probably would have guessed the gender marker that I chose. Their ask made me feel like I had agency, even in the face of a bureaucratic process that doesn’t allow me to opt-out. Also, said flight was vital for participation in the program in question, and airlines are not known for bending rules. They really did need the information. (It’s not appropriate to ask if you don’t need it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;if-you-cant-control-acknowledge&quot;&gt;If you can’t control, acknowledge.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you as an organizer don’t have an option to make a particular part of your event more inclusive. The contract was signed on the space and there are no gender-neutral/all-gender restrooms. The conference chair could not be budged from an introduction style. The sponsorship required use of a space that forces participants to show government ID.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have had to make a choice that you know is not inclusive, acknowledging it can help by making clear that you realize the outcome is not good.  At the very least, you can say this to invitees who you know are non-binary. You probably also should consider saying it to everyone, but I’m aware that can feel like a big ask.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A script:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Hey, here’s your welcome packet. Also, I’m not sure if this is relevant to you or not, but we were unable to secure space that has gender-neutral restrooms this year. It’s in our requirements for next year, for sure. I’m sorry if this causes you any inconvenience, and please let us know if you have any trouble.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This script doesn’t assume that the person needs a gender-neutral bathroom, but makes clear that you are thinking about it and will fix it in the future. Do not say you will fix it if you won’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;if-you-screw-up-apologize-and-take-steps-to-fix-it&quot;&gt;If you screw up, apologize and take steps to fix it.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, American society is incredibly reinforcing of the gender binary, so it likely that all of us will screw up at some point. When someone screws up in a way that makes me feel othered or unwelcome at an event, I want at least two things from them: an individual apology, that makes clear that they realize why what they did was bad; and an explanation of the steps they plan on taking to fix it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some scripts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I’m so sorry I screwed up your pronouns when I was introducing you to our sponsor. I realize that probably have put you an uncomfortable position. In the future, I’ll practice beforehand to make sure I get them correct.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I realized when we divided the room up into men and women, I included you with the men because you are masculine presenting. I erased your non-binary identity. I’m sorry. In the future, I’ll divide the room in half in some other way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;specific-guidance&quot;&gt;Specific guidance:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Location, space and logistics:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Default to not collecting gender information from people at registration. If you do collect it, make it non-mandatory, explain what you need it for (e.g., “to track the gender makeup of the conference over time”), and use a text entry form as opposed to radio buttons or checkboxes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gender-neutral restrooms are necessary. It is 2018. It is well past time to make your restroom situation more friendly for everyone. Choose restaurants and event spaces that have gender-free bathroom options, ideally including single occupancy. Or add gender-neutral bathrooms yourself by converting binary-gendered bathrooms. (Some folks prefer the term “all gender”, some folks prefer “gender free.” Personally, I would suggest “gender-neutral.” Frankly, it’s more important that you have them than what you call them.) If these restrooms are not easy to find, or located in a different place than gendered restrooms, include where they are in any printed materials. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid locations that require showing government ID to enter. I’m aware that there is an unfortunate trend for tech companies to require government IDs to sign into buildings. See if this requirement can be waived for your event.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Also avoid locations that require a binary sex identification in advance in order to attend. Unfortunately, that can mean that some government buildings that require pre-registration/a background check will not be open to you. However, if you avoid these activities up front, you can avoid putting a trans or non-binary person in a position where they have to choose whether attending is worth submitting such an identification or accidentally outing themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If offering schwag, identify t-shirts as fitted and straight cut, not men’s and women’s! Don’t make assumptions about which style someone wants. (And offer &lt;a href=&quot;http://geekfeminism.wikia.com/wiki/T-shirts&quot;&gt;both&lt;/a&gt;.) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt; Language and people:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bare minimum: have a Code of Conduct that includes harassment based on gender identity and enforce it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Non-binary people are not necessarily women. Femme non-binary people (people who present femininely) are not all women. Grouping non-binary folks or femme folks in with women is erasing. If you are hosting a women-in-X event, make clear whether non-binary or femme folks are welcome. Do not expect that the term women includes femme folks. (For more information on this, see Kat Marchán’s amazing post &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@maybekatz/on-the-design-of-womens-spaces-72bf8f396dc0&quot;&gt;on the design of women spaces&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Skip the phrases “ladies,” “girls,” and “chicks.” Don’t use biological parts as stand-in for gender: “pussy”, “xx” to mean a women’s event, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try not to use binary-reinforcing statements like “ladies and gentlemen” or “we’re dividing the group into men and women.” &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When calling on people whose names you don’t know, avoid gendered assumptions, like “the lady on the end” or “the man in the red shirt.” Instead, use “the person at the end of the row with short hair” or “the person with the beard in the red shirt.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt; Everyone’s favorite topic, pronouns:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have nametags and politely suggest people write their pronouns. Everyone. Not just people who look gender non-conforming. Or, alternately, have &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiscon.net/2016/05/22/pronouns-yours-mine-ours/&quot;&gt;pronoun stickers&lt;/a&gt;, and point them out to folks if at registration. Include a “just use my name” option, and an option for people to write in their own information.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t guess people’s pronouns. Look for an indication (like a ribbon or them written on a nametag), check their online profile, or use they/them as a default. Some in-person events may have to explain to their attendees that this should be the norm. It is better for this to come from people in positions of authority rather than making individuals who want their pronouns respected do it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If introducing a speaker, ask them to send you introductory bio, then read it. Ad-lib only if you can nail their pronouns. It is much better if someone just straight up reads a bio then if they attempt to improvise and get pronouns wrong. This happens to me regularly and it’s fucking horrible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If someone’s pronouns are uncomfortable or unfamiliar for you, it is your job to practice them and get them right. If you screw them up in front of that person, apologize briefly and move on. Do not just ignore them. If they correct you, take this an opportunity to do better. It is inappropriate to explain to them how uncomfortable it is for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Trips and travel:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Going through TSA screening can be dangerous and traumatic for many trans and non-binary folks, especially those who have had surgery or otherwise taken physical transition steps. Some non-binary and trans people can face significant harassment on public transportation, and may prefer to take a ride-hailing service or a cab. So generally, being flexible around travel and especially around travel reimbursements is a good way to make your event more inclusive.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide individual lodging for people. Do not make people share rooms. Do not make gendered assumptions about lodging. Do not split up people into a “girls” floor and a “guys” floor.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many non-binary folks may face discrimination or hostility in their workplaces, making it more difficult for them to receive paying jobs. So the best practice of reimbursing people as soon as possible for travel (ideally after booking, not waiting until they complete the trip) or providing non-reimbursement options for booking may make your event more inclusive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;following-up&quot;&gt;Following Up:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you a non-binary person and there’s something that would make you feel more comfortable at events that I missed? Please let me know so I can add it! kendra.serra@gmail.com or &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/KendraSerra&quot;&gt;KendraSerra&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re an event organizer and you’ve found this content useful, I encourage you to make a significant donation to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://srlp.org/&quot;&gt;Sylvia Rivera Law Project&lt;/a&gt;, which works to guarantee that all people are free to self-determine gender identity and expression, regardless of income or race, and without facing harassment, discrimination or violence. If you would like to have me consult about making your specific event more inclusive, drop me a line at kendra.serra@gmail.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="nonbinary" /><category term="eventplanner" /><category term="sotiredofthisbullshit" /><summary type="html">When I attend events, I’m often the first out non-binary person that the organizers have ever invited. Many times, I am the first out non-binary person they have ever met.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">57.3%</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/02/20/573.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="57.3%" /><published>2018-02-20T13:00:26-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-20T13:00:26-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/02/20/573</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/02/20/573.html">&lt;p&gt;Last August, Jon Hanson asked me, as an alum, to give a talk to a group of Harvard Law School 1Ls about “life in the law.” It was one of the hardest talks I’ve ever given, because it’s some of the subject matter that’s still the rawest for me. It’s been sitting on my hard drive for a while, and although it fills me with anxiety, I figure it’s long past time I share it publicly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure data-orig-width=&quot;900&quot; data-orig-height=&quot;444&quot; class=&quot;tmblr-full&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://66.media.tumblr.com/79d517a5d929aa1d6123dec8275888b8/tumblr_inline_p491koS2271rrgb56_540.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; data-orig-width=&quot;900&quot; data-orig-height=&quot;444&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November 2016, I was sitting in a hotel room in Pittsburgh and I had just found out that I failed the California bar, just like 57.3% of other people who took it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alex, one of my best friends from law school, and I took the bar together. Among 1500 test takers in Sacramento, California, we were randomly placed two seats apart. I’m on the phone with her when we get our results. She’s convinced that the computer system failed, that there’d been some sort of mistake. After all, she walked out halfway through the first session (leaving me panicking on her behalf in the test room), and she’s passed. Her faith in my ability to make up California law on the spot was touching, but I knew that if I’d failed, I’d deserve it. I hadn’t studied hard enough. I had been convinced that adrenaline would pull me through on the day of–but the reality is that relying on sheer willpower is a bad strategy for closed-book high-stakes testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not the only one who has failed the California bar. Every year, &lt;em&gt;Above the Law&lt;/em&gt; publishes a list: Hillary Clinton, Michelle Obama, Kamala Harris, Kathleen Sullivan. Ridiculously successful people who were probably too busy doing useful things rather than studying for the test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So back to Pittsburgh. Alex stayed on the phone with me, as I typed my exam number in again and again. She’s sure something went wrong. I’m sure California’s 42.7% pass rate had caught up with me. The next day, another friend posted about her bar experience on Facebook. She wrote: “…You only fail if you give up so maybe I won’t say I failed but I also did not pass the California bar exam. Since Friday, I’ve been waiting for the tears to come. I’ve been waiting for devastation or anger. But it’s Monday, and that hasn’t happened.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn’t brave like her. I kept silent publicly, and I cried privately. I avoided questions about it, and as the exam where I would retake it approached, I got the bar exam mansplained to me because I didn’t want to admit I’d already taken it and failed. I was convinced that all of my successes would be erased if people found out I failed the bar. That bar failure revealed the truth of who I was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be charitable to myself, there is a reason. Law is a status-driven profession. It would be foolish to tell you otherwise. It would be a lie to tell you that Harvard Law School does not open doors for you or that the right words on your resume will not get you at least an interview. My worry was at least justifiable, if not excused. (That’s a criminal law joke, you’ll get it after next semester.) I worried ceaselessly, for months, about what would the words “pending admission to the California bar” would do to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is all too easy to believe that what you do is who you are. That success is measured in acceptances, grades, study group invitations, and the law review competition. But Harvard attendance does not make you a better person. Depending upon your resume and test scores to define your self-worth will lead to crying by yourself in a hotel room, ashamed to admit to your boss that you failed a fucking standardized test.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I recommend you try your best to reject the idea that your successes will determine your value as a person. What I try to tell myself is that failing to pass the bar the first time doesn’t diminish me, doesn’t make me worth less because my worth does not come from my ability to overcome the hurdles of our profession. I fail at convincing myself of this a lot. But I still try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’ll say it to you: you cannot control what other people do, where the curve falls, or what California’s cut score is. So do not make your own care for yourself contingent upon it. You do not deserve respect or care because you will someday pass the bar, or because you may get good grades, or even because you are in the best section. You deserve respect, kindness, and care because you are a person. Your value does not come from your ability to be a lawyer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I contemplate lessons I have learned about the law, I wish someone had told me that no matter how well you do in law school, or in life, tying your self-worth to how well your accomplishments stack up to other people’s expectations sets an impossible standard that you will do yourself harm trying to reach. And also, the California bar is not that easy, so you might want to buy some flashcards.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Last August, Jon Hanson asked me, as an alum, to give a talk to a group of Harvard Law School 1Ls about “life in the law.” It was one of the hardest talks I’ve ever given, because it’s some of the subject matter that’s still the rawest for me. It’s been sitting on my hard drive for a while, and although it fills me with anxiety, I figure it’s long past time I share it publicly. </summary></entry></feed>